Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Postcards and Trading Cards ALBA.242
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Postcards and Trading Cards
circa 1936-1938, 1951, 1970s, 1980-2000s
1936-1939
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
ALBA.242
2 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 2 half manuscript boxes.
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Postcards and Trading Cards is composed of postcards and trading cards related to the Spanish Civil War (1936-1939). Many of the postcards in this collection were created as propaganda by combatant groups or were made by organizations such as the Red Cross to solicit donations and other forms of support. Most postcards in this collection were created by or in support of the Republican side of the conflict. Postcards are illustrated in different artistic styles, including Socialist realism, and some show photographs. Most postcards were never used. Some trading cards in the collection were created by companies such as the Bowman Gum Company and supported the Republicans, while other sets of trading cards were pro-Nationalist.
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Postcards and Trading Cards (1936-2000s) is comprised of over 400 postcards and trading cards related to the Spanish Civil War (1936-1939). The materials in this collection were produced as visual propaganda to garner support for the Nationalists or the Republicans. Postcards were made by combatant groups, for example the Unión General de Trabajadores de España, and official propaganda ministries, as well as by humanitarian aid groups like the Red Cross, and organizations around the world who supported one side of the war, including the United Socialist Youth (Juventudes Socialistas Unificadas), which supported the Republicans. Some postcards were created to solicit donations, send to politicians, or draw attention to specific causes including refugee children and war prisoners. Most postcards in this collection were created by or in support of the Republican side of the conflict. Many of the postcards are in Catalan and were made by the Partit Socialista Unificat de Catalunya and the Commissariat de Propaganda de la Generalitat de Catalunya. Some postcards in the collection demonstrate support for the Basque Country (Euskadi).
This collection also includes some postcards from Spain that are not directly related to the Spanish Civil War, including postcards with photographs of Madrid, portraits of Catalonian men, and postcards depicting the traditional dress of various regions in Spain. There are also postcards depicting Spanish Civil War memorials, postcards created by the International Brigade Archives, and postcards made to publicize exhibitions of Spanish Civil War propaganda posters.
Many postcards in this collection feature graphics in the Socialist realism style. Others were made using other methods of illustration, and a small number show photographs. Some postcards have notes written on them and were posted, but most of the postcards in this collection are blank.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
There is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials. The accession numbers associated with these items are 2001.005 and 2019.016.
Arrangement
This collection has not been physically arranged by an archivist. Materials have been grouped by theme where appropriate and are listed in alphabetical order in the file listing.
Separated Materials
A series of trading cards entitled Children's Crusade Against Communism were separated and described as a separate collection, the Children's Crusade Against Communism Trading Cards TAM 786.
Historical Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Postcards and Trading Cards contains postcards and trading cards related to the 1936-1939 conflict between Spanish Nationalists under General Francisco Franco's military Junta and a coalition of socialist, communist, anarchist, and separatist groups known as the Republicans. Many of the groups who joined the Republicans were a part of the political left and had supported the Popular Front government of the Second Spanish Republic (1931-1939).
This collection was assembled by Tamiment Library staff.
Appraisal
In 2024, a box of reproductions of one original postcard in the collection was discarded.
Political postcards.; Trading cards; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Nationalism and art -- Spain -- History -- 20th century; Art -- Political aspects -- Spain -- History -- 20th century; Unión General de Trabajadores de España; Bowman Gum Company (1927-1956); Catalonia (Spain). Comissariat de Propaganda; Juventud Socialista Unificada; Partit Socialista Unificat de Catalunya; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional; International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement
- !Amnistia¡ -- Miguel Angel Zamora Anton en la Prision Carabanchel Madrid, circa 1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Chisholm-Larsson Gallery Exhibition Postcards, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Chisholm-Prats Gallery "Original Posters" exhibition postcards, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Costumbres Andaluza por M. Bertuchi, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Costumbres Valencianas por C. Ruana Llopis, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Foreign Support for Republicans, circa 1936-1939, undated
  - British postcards, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Christmas cards to aid Spain, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - French postcards, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gum Inc. trading cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Holiday Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Horrors of War Trading Cards, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - International Prisoners in Spain--"Buena Suerte", undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Pre-written postcards to U.N. Secretary General Trygve Lie, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pre-written postcards to U.S. politicians, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Swedish postcard, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Union of Democratic Nations, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - U.S. postcards, 1936-1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 9, Box 4, Folder 6)
- Humanitarian Groups, circa 1936-1939, undated
  - Ajut Infantil de Reraguarda, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Child refugees, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Comissió oficial d'ajut Euzkadi, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Comité de Ayuda a Euzkadi Y Norte, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Comité Nacional de Mujeres Antifascistas, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Equipo al Servicio de la Infancia Amenazada, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Instituto Nacional de Prevision, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Last Commisar of the Grupo de Evacuation No. 1, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Proteje los Huérfanos, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Socors Roig, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Vida del Soldado--Soccoro Rojo, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- International Brigades, 1938, undated
  - Comisariado de las Brigadas Internationales, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - International Brigade Archive postcards, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - International Brigade memorials, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Primera de Mayo, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tarjeta Postal de Campaña, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Nationalist Trading Cards, circa 1936-1950, undated
  - La Guerra en España, circa 1936-1950, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Los Salvadores de España, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Parque Plaza de Cana Ejas, Alicante, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Madrid, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Portraits of Nationalists, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Portraits of prominent Communists, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Pro-Fascist Italian postcards, 1940s, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Republican Combatants, circa 1936-1951, undated
  - Agrupacion Socialista Madrileña, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dirección General de Carabineros, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - El Ejercito de Levante, October 1938 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Estampas de la Guerra en Euzkadi, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Frente Popular de Madrid, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Forjadores de Imperio, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Herois de la Joventut--Lina Odena, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Junta Delegada de Defensa de Madrid, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Juventudes Socialistas Unificadas, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Partido Sindicalista España, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Portraits, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Servicio de Hospitales, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Unión General de Trabajadores and Partit Socialista Unificat postcards, circa 1936-1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-4, Box 3, Folder 23, Box 4, Folder 3)
- Republican Propaganda, circa 1936-1950, undated
  - Altavoz del Frente, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cartoon postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Commissariat de Propaganda Generalitat de Catalunya, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Con el Ejercicio Físico--Luchareis sin esfuerzo, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Edició No. 22 del Commissariat de Propaganda de la Generalitat de Catalunya, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ediciones Éspañolas, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Epopeyas de la Guerra, 1939; undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Box 4, Folder 4)
  - La Españade Burgos, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - El Fascismo Pretende Encarcelar España, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Flota República Espanyola, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Front D'Aragó, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ministerio de Propaganda, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Los Nacionales, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Procés de la Revolució de Espanya, undated (Box 1, Folder 2, Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Proclamación de la República Trading Cards, circa 1936-1950, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Puzol, Puebla de Farnals, Puig, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Republica Española, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Subsecretaría de Propaganda, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Tipu Catalá de Girona, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)